no there was there was a certain Spirit
which uh I don't know if it's been
dampened uh well certainly in some of
the individuals involved but hopefully
not in the uh youngsters yeah but uh uh
uh there's a certain Spirit of Discovery
and uh of the unknown exploring the
unknown that that that is just man makes
you want to you know wake up in the
morning or in the night and jump in a
lab and and and see you know what will
come forth and uh and this is a good
thing this is a really good thing what
advice would you have for someone saying
there's someone listening right now they
may be a junior senior in high school
they're interested in lasers interested
in Optics and particularly they would
love to one day be a holograph and
create Holograms what advice would you
have for them to choose that as a career
path oh besides keeping the day job yeah
um uh no I I say that with the some
regret um well it's interesting you know
in terms of of the distribution first of
all there are some uh sort of meat and
potatoes aspects of holography which I'm
sure your listeners are probably aware
of uh involving uh holographic
non-destructive testing and some uh
engineering applications and nowadays
the idea of creating Holograms that are
simply templates for you know creating
Nano structures and things like that
these are the worlds in which these uh
uh these kids are going to be uh you
know um graduating into um where the
Hologram is basically um a tool for uh
any number of other things rather than
uh let's say anart art object per se or
or a device for advertising um there are
so many more what I call these meet VES
applications of hology which are um uh
Holograms applied to different
engineering challenges or biomedical
engineering challenges and things like
that where where you know we have a
result at the end of the line that is
something other than aesthetic some
people say that you know art in the
context of art you know some people say
that it has to be absolutely useless to
be fine artart in other words have no
other purpose to be fine art and there's
a value to that there's a value to you
know the you know to have a a sacred
clown you know in the Hy culture or
whatever you know the idea of having you
know there's there's a reason for that
sort of aesthetic um but on the other
hand uh if it's uh something where you
want to for sure absolutely positively
make money um and a living at it uh then
then then perhaps some of the so-called
meat and potato applications are is
Charles vest still the the president of
of MIT I I don't have a clue okay
because at one point he was and I think
we should all be proud of that he's of
course a holograph he published
holographic interferometry like the
Bible of that many years ago oh really
yeah where there was news and uh well he
was I Believe instrumental with Steve
bent yeah I was going to say he's
probably been uh very supportive of the
spatial Imaging group up there oh yeah
and of course the the the acquisition of
the Museum of waterest collection yes uh
uh really from the depths and throws of
uh of uh of being dispersed to the for
Corners if I don't know if you go over
that kind of history with one of your
holot talks but but there was a point in
which museal holography collection was
going to be uh
dispersed uh in in in not a good way and
uh and Dr Benton and and Charles
Fest pivotal and and securing it for the
MIT Museum which your listeners can
always go look at yes one in Boston
which is nice yeah I I'm just so
surprised that in a metropolitan area
the size of New York City that there's
no Museum phography anymore I just you
know I'm just dumbfounded with that well
you know this considering what is there
greater curiosity you know and I mean I
was on Eastman kodak's website uh the
museum that is Eastman House's website
and I've been there in person it's
wonderful but uh if you go on the
website and you look at the history of
photographic systems and you go back
where um you'll see a camera I was
looking at a couple months ago it's made
in 1852 the first one I could find that
was 3D a stereo camera made of you know
brass and wood and glass and funky
beautiful looking things and and taking
3D pictures back in 1852 if I recall
correctly and so now here we are 150
years precisely later and you don't go
into uh any everybody's house and see oh
there's you know a stereogram of the
grandkids you know I'm not even talking
Holograms now I'm just talking about
stereophotography a perfectly viable
wonderful Imaging system for 3D that
anyone can do with any camera you don't
need a stereo camera you just take two
pictures as your audience might know you
know slightly offset views and um uh so
here's a perfectly good
three-dimensional Imaging system 150
years old and yet has not thoroughly
permeated uh uh you know the culture and
so um of course we have you know 3D IMAX
and still we have view Masters and all
that but I'm talking about something
where people enjoy it among themselves
yes and shoot their own so if we have
150 years that stereography isn't fully
fully integrated into the average
person's home uh then you know what is
to say are we to say about you know the
holography and when and if will happen
so so I scratch my head along with the
next guy figuring trying to figure out
why is Nar a hologram on every home you
know a stereogram in every
garage I mean it's wonderful and now of
course it's uh cheap I read a brilliant
article by Andrew pepper uh about
holography and architecture and um uh uh
I'm sure if you do a search for that
you'll find it on the web it's really
really good article uh just a couple
days ago really about a week ago and uh
and he mentions in it um that some of
the expectations that were created in
the early days uh caused uh and this is
terrible paraphrasing because he was
very eloquent about it uh but uh it
caused in the consumer you know the
general Public's mind you know this kind
of expectation that maybe overshadowed
the reality to a point where this is why
there's a sort of deflated oh well you
know and uh uh but I remember there were
years that went by where we would say to
each other's among a lot of first that
you know next year you know it's going
to be the big one you know then next
year it's going to be yeah and it's went
on for a decade and here we are with
gray hair yeah um well of course you
know Holograms have permeated the uh
environment uh for God's sakes I've got
I've seen them as litter these days I
was in a parking lot of a Denny's a
couple years ago and and they were just
like you know
litter and uh which is sad but uh there
they are and um uh uh no it's it's the
period I I I would call you know the
Chach ification you know holography well
it's happening big in education but once
again it's almost like using holography
as a tool you know oh I'm glad to hear
that tool you know I did not know that
oh absolutely full courses so you can
graduate as a the doctor in holography
oh no not to that point we're talking
about uh uh supplementary uh classroom
activities in science and physics and
things of that nature to the elementary
or mainly High School uh mainly High
School yeah seen a lot of science with
it you know and uh some of the projects
that I've been involved with with
disadvantaged youth seems to be uh taken
off too oh that's wonderful yeah Florida
Duval County in Florida actually I'll be
down in Florida November you're kidding
yeah to oh we got to get together yeah I
don't know how far devolve it's in
Jacksonville I don't know how far that
is got be closer than where you are now
well absolutely it's closer yeah yeah so
uh I'll give you a buzz before I head
down for that so you're going to make
Holograms with the kids uh meeting with
a few of the community colleges and the
Deval County School District I was down
there uh one time before there's a a
teacher down there that is involved with
communication technology and he has a
wonderful holography program for oh this
is great I'm so happy to hear that yeah
so uh that's starting to be mirrored in
other areas as well yeah if I can help
just let me know that sound neat yeah in
fact I will let him know you know that
you're so close close by I I really
enjoy that in fact more than anything I
I I uh I learned so much when I started
teaching that I never expected to learn
much uh when I started T yeah that's
that's most actually of what I did for
many years uhhuh you know through
museums and you know science museums and
stuff put food on the table you know but
this isn't my interview this is yours
okay go ahead Let's uh let's get back to
uh I I know you had mentioned earlier
that uh you had sent an email you know
listing a few of the things that you
want to covered I did go back into the
email program I didn't see that so if
there's anything didn't work hard on
that Frank I know you probably did no
actually there's nothing there unless
it's something that I didn't click on or
whatever but uh as of 230 I wasn't able
to find it and oh I see here it has an
odd uh title I'm looking at it now what
does it say it doesn't say anything
about how I can enlarge my breasts or
anything does it no no because I get a
lot of
those okay I can look at it and use it
as a as a reference here go ahead um uh
for the students out there who starting
to make Holograms uh make a note of the
importance of optic schematics and
triple checking yourself the idea that
whatever you're doing make yourself a
little sketch it doesn't have to be
elaborate whether you're using
continuous wave heis or or diodes or
whatever make a little sketch of what
you're doing make your measurements you
know little tape measure centimeter
measure like a Tailor's measure and uh
take some notes because you'll find from
time to time you'll uh you'll do
something really neat and you want to
repeat that experiment so no matter how
simple they are uh some kind of optical
schematic of what you've done and as far
as triple checking yourself well it's
just a good way to save uh save on
materials yeah measure measure twice cut
once yeah well I like to measure three
times because then you can go two out of
three um that was something I wanted to
to bring out um and uh uh
well
um take your time yeah yeah oh you cut
out the blank space
uh no we're all right I mean you
know well it's interesting um I've got
uh uh one of the reasons for some of
these somewhat you know sort of campy or
kchy or sort of silly things that I've
done uh like the you know smelling
hologram and stuff uh and the macaroni
piece I guess people know um uh it's
just that we take ourselves so darn
seriously um so it's important to to
lighten up yeah and uh and so that's why
I like doing sometimes uh you know
somewhat silly things in Holograms
because it's just all so darn serious by
the time you know you spit Your beams
and you get all your other stuff right
you pay the rent and everything bam uh
you know it's hard to uh to uh to add
some levity to the situation so every
hologram doesn't have to uh describe the
meaning of life no but if you you can
send me a copy of that particular one
I'd like to see that you got seems like
a lot of them try interesting yeah I'd
love to read some of the descriptions
not just with holography but anything in
art you know as far as what the artist
was trying to convey right and um I get
lost sometimes to tell you the truth I
just get up in the morning and do a day
worth of work that type of person you
know so I'll read these descriptions and
well it's funny because actually I did
make a note that perhaps the uh perhaps
the uh the ultimate impact of of
holography will be you know the so-call
holographic
Paradigm the idea that you
know hey you know I'm sorry I I don't
know how to disable should I answer that
Frank uh that may be the big contract
why don't you answer it and get back to
me I'll put this on funny guy hold
on hello hello hey okay we're we're
we're eating up megabytes aren't we
that's okay are we going straight to the
hard drive or you going to actual tape
or what you I go I go right to the hard
drive I also have an optical recorder
too but I we're rolling now yes we are
oh I apologize oh that's okay for what
uh well eating up gigs I don't know this
so what I saying is not disabling the uh
call waiting I suppose to call it okay
what I started say was that um it it
took me a while to figure this out but
perhaps the ultimate impact of
holography will be completely invisible
and weightless MH have nothing to do
with making Holograms that tell you
whether uh welds are separating or or
selling uh toothpaste or uh uh you know
pop musicians and all that good stuff um
mainly uh just the principle of
holography has applied to our
understanding how information is
dispersed through univers is a paradigm
that's been K around for quite a while
and there are whole books on it as I'm
sure some of your audience is aware of
uh but it took me a while to figure out
that that was really important stuff
versus uh all the actual hard
applications of
holography uh you know hard copy
applications where you're actually
making something the concept is uh is
maybe more more lasting and more
powerful than anything we can actually
do with the medium so uh um this is
interesting this is a very interesting
aspect that again as I said it's
weightless and invisible but very much
real
yeah yes very much very much in the old
days you know when I was first making
Holograms I felt that I was at Ground
Zero and that all these people you know
and with robes and incense and
everything they were they were talking
about this stuff back in the mid '70s it
seemed like you know what the heck did
they know about
Holograms and then all of a sudden CU
they were adopting the Hologram as their
you know their Paradigm from explaining
different various things but then time
after I did a little research and I met
a few individuals I I started uh who
were on the subject um I I started
realizing that this is really powerful
stuff and and it's way way uh important
yeah back back with Carl pryr and uh oh
yeah I spoke I've spoken with him yeah
and uh David bone yeah I think Ken
Wilbur did a wonderful book on that I
think it's called the holographic
Paradigm and other paradoxes as well
yeah no they're very they're very
interesting and of course for ancient
for those in the a who are unfamiliar
with what we're talking about cuz that's
possible yeah um uh there the idea that
you take a hologram break it into little
pieces and see the entire scenario in
every little piece because of the
dispersed information storage aspect of
holography that you can actually break a
hologram piece off and see the whole
scene that was pictured in the you know
Frank sometimes you and I forget about
stuff that people are unaware of that
yeah when they're first coming to this
um and uh uh in any event it's one of
the most powerful aspects of uh of how
different holography is from photography
the fact that you can break off a little
piece of a hologram and see the whole
scene pictured in that little piece and
uh because the Hologram is like a window
into that scenario and and uh so this
has led to corollaries with um these
ancient Eastern philosophical tenants
that uh that suggest that uh that
information about everything is
everywhere and transcend space and time
and you simply have to get in the right
mindset to access that information but
it nonetheless fill all space and time
so it's very interesting uh having a
hard copy version of example yeah
thought you used to call Point table
example one of that phenomen the famous
quotes for that is the brain is a
hologram interpreting a holographic
Universe I believe is that's a good one
that's a good one well it would make
sense that if you were going to build an
antenna for something that it would have
to uh correspond uh to the waveform that
you're trying to receive yes exactly
good thinking yeah
sharp um to unrelated but may not be
okay and I've always wanted to ask this
you do so much commercial work and I
have to phrase this properly for the
show but uh do you do you ever get a lot
of calls for any adult work you know
considering the the explosion of adult
material on the internet sure and it's
mostly visual yeah the two main reasons
for trees dying uh in the world being
cut down uh for paper are uh uh
pornography and uh computer manuals
those are the two biggest Eaters of
paper of trees right now on Earth but
seriously folks um uh well once in a
while let's call them erotic you know
yeah that that happens from time to time
yeah uh the big fell who used to be sort
of the king of all that sort of thing
was out in the west coast his name was
Peter Claudius and in the early days of
Multiplex he was the guy who explored
that I think more than anyone yeah
there's even a snapshot of him with his
so-called Holo blow machine uh in on my
website if you wander among the holoid
okay you'll see Peter standing there
with his hand on one of the knobs so to
speak okay they're knobs they're door
knobs nothing is perfectly uh perfectly
clean yeah did you ever do any of the um
360 inte oh my God yeah oh what a
wonderful format sure absolutely I think
I produced the first cyclic one in which
there was no beginning or end and it was
fun to explore that uh back pre you know
the digital domain
it was a portrait of a guy named Romos
oh okay yeah and so I filmed him uh
sitting on cross-legged in my studio on
this turntable and as he rotated around
to a frontal
view uh we stopped the turntable and I
did a slow zoom into his eyes and then
and then uh uh then you notice this
thing was appearing in sort of third eye
area and his eyes faded out and as his
eyes faded out this thing faded up and
uh you re and it was you realized it was
spinning the circular design mandala
pattern and it was spinning and you were
zooming a away from it and just by about
the time that you had a full view of the
full mandala spinning in the middle of
360 this image of this guy sitting in
full Lotus position from seen from
behind starts fading up from the center
of the mandala and then the mandala
Fades out and you're back to uh him
arcing around and looking you in the eye
again so it's a hologram that had no
real beginning or end and it was an
interesting experiment I did with uh
Lynwood dun uh did the optical out in
Hollywood and started to apply Hollywood
effects to uh to holographic stereograms
this kind of seemed like a no-brainer at
the time and and so basically the tale
of the a element of his portrait was
faded and dissolved into the head of the
B element which was uh the mandala and
then at the tale of the B element it was
fad and dissolved back in so that's the
way the the a so that's the way the the
film was prepared and it basically it's
nothing it's an ancient thing in
Hollywood but it was kind of newe to
holography to go through that kind of
optical handstand to produce the
origination materials and I'm trying to
think of who printed that uh holograph
if if listeners want to see a sample of
that um you have an animated gift right
on your main page that oh okay yeah but
that's you're looking out of a80
frames it's a good idea much smoother
when you're looking at 1,80 frames yeah
yeah anything else you want to add to
the interview Mark um well nothing
occurs to me right off the you know it's
it's one of these things I'm sure when I
hang up I say oh man I could have told
him about that but um yeah I guess that
we could talk just for a minute about
about you
know when I first got into holography I
realized that some of the absolute best
people making Holograms technically were
uh totally uh uh unaware of what art
made an art
image and all that so I kind of wanted
to bridge that that that right there
would seemed to be the challenge at the
get-go was to be able to technically
execute these things that with with some
aesthetic that was you know powerful as
well as opposed to just like well here's
a hologram of my uh you know salt and
pepper shaker or my Forks or whatever
yeah and uh and and while it is very
intriguing to see a three-dimensional
image of of an object uh that may not be
present anymore you know in the
holographic image that's very
intriguing there's more to be done with
the medium than simply
three-dimensionally capturing things
that you can imagine in the first place
or even capture in other ways three
dimensionally and uh there was a fellow
by the name of MC aser who a very famous
artist uh I'm sure you people in your
audience have seen his work familiar
with his work and in one of his books he
talks about uh um um uh approaches to
Infinity is what he calls it's a little
monograph it's like a page and a half
long in the beginning of one of those
famous eer books and he calls in
approaches to Infinity he describes how
uh when he was originally schooled as a
draftsman his his main task was trying
to make that eye brain hand connection
and convey that which his Mind's Eye
could grasp onto paper and that was what
he had to learn at first well once he
got that down real well um uh this sort
of kind of bored him and he started uh
imagining thinking about well how can I
convey things that the Mind's Eye can't
grasp such as infinity and this began
like a 30 40y year uh um effort in so
many various work works that I'm sure
many of the viewers have seen uh uh uh
in which he tried to convey this concept
of infinity he says to himself well I
need a piece of paper of infinite size
so that's not going to work somehow in a
small area I'm going to have to evoke
that feeling and and that became his
Pursuit and um so I mentioned this in
the context of holography only because
um uh we all like for instance you have
a hologram of some puppy dogs or a
hologram of uh you know a clown or
whatever we can all kind of imagine what
a clown looks like in 3D or puppy dog or
whatever uh salt and pepper shakers um
it's the stuff that we can't imagine in
3D that I find so interesting uh to use
holography as a medium for that's why
personally I'm I'm I'm partial to
abstracts uh abstract images just the
beauty of the color and the light and
the purity of the color uh that one can
do in the kinetics that you can apply
I've I've done quite a number of
holograms like that but um uh it's
actually my favorite stuff is is the
nonrepresentational hologram where
they're not necessarily representing a
three-dimensional thing but the medium
is just used as a fluid way to paint
with light that moves yes and uh and
that it would be impossible to do with
any other medium yeah exactly exactly
whereas a good stereogram of you know
the puppy dogs whatever uh is pretty
much the same thing um so so that's
something that maybe people can be uh uh
launched into some of your students are
uh early practitioners what have you
well maybe in the older practitioners
yeah um but uh I enjoy that aspect of
holography that you can that you can
approach the visualization of things
that cannot be um
imagined and is is is I think more
interesting I've done a couple of
holograms like that and I think that
that's that's cool of stuff you know
we're like big game fishing in the in
the you know in the Dark Void of pure
research you know then stuff pops up
yeah when you're not in pursuit of uh of
applied science or or art in particular
stuff stuff does show up Dr invented
holography discovered it if you will by
so-called accident some say in that he
was really trying to improve two
dimensional imaging technology of the
electron microscopy yes so uh he
inadvertently or serendipitously
discovered this threedimensional Imaging
medium so my contention is that what
will a holograph in wrote one day en
route to trying to improve holography
the threedimensional imaging technology
of hary discovered by so-call vent or
serendipitously so it's that the hope of
that
next uh window into something that we've
never seen before that made show up and
this is why I said earlier uh whether
they're 15 or they're 60 years old it
makes no difference my oldest student
has been 72 years old and my youngest
student was 8 years old and uh I I don't
think that um that age has anything to
do with it uh it's just a matter of
paying real close attention yeah maybe
time travel will be the holography of
the
future who knows you
know travel and and that it's so
farfetched but I'm sure holography was
farfetched at one time as well just as
farfetched well you know there there a
wacky uh wacky uh directions that things
are going in terms of projection
technology you know uh uh uh direct
right to Reta I think is is is has a big
future it already exists of course uh
where you pop on the glasses and the the
little di are writing writing the images
on your retinus but it appears as a
giant threedimensional image in space in
front of you uh so that's that already
exists um while it hasn't been made
super popular they're you know under
defense contracts for those things not
sure you can actually run out and buy
one but they're they're they exist for
some years now we're we're you don't
require a giant screen at all the
glasses are actually projecting writing
the image and rewriting it onto your RS
directly yeah so I think other
directions for for this sort of thing
for you know may uh it may evolve into
something else I don't know about the
time travel par Frank that's yeah it's a
little farf that's very ambitious
yes where can someone see your work do
you have anything exhibited anywhere
across the country right now yeah
there's some stuff I know that I believe
still in like for instance in Canada I
think they still have a giant dizzy over
at the uh at the uh Ontario Science
Museum okay and uh uh up until recently
there was some stuff in I I don't really
know where all the stuff is do you have
a gallery down in Florida I have I
maintain a gallery down here now uhhuh
and uh well tell the listeners about
that because I'm sure there's some
people in Florida that were listen oh
sure well anyone can just go to the
website you know diamond images.com and
then and then give me a ring and say hey
I'd love to come over because it's not
like open to the public in general okay
it's open but by Point yeah um I I set
up a first gallery of hram South New
York here back in 75 I think it was and
ran that for about 12 years and so that
was pretty neat um it was actually a
place where you could come in and see
the work of holograph from all over the
world really not just my own um for
about 12 years and um uh maybe 100
Holograms at any given time on display
and that's always been fun and uh still
maintain a collection but uh and I'm
from time to time do uh you know uh not
a traveling show per se but a show that
can
travel um and uh well you've certainly
done a lot of work and you're really U
out there as far as continuing with the
projects all the time yeah it's amazing
how some of these things you know you
have to kind of stick uh stick with your
dreams because uh some of them take a
long time to come to fruition yeah yeah
I guess you just have to find your place
I found my Niche I think with the uh
amateurs and hobbyists and education end
which uh I think some people uh in the
early days were interested in the
education but I don't think there was a
lot of interest in anybody being an
amateur or hobbyist but I saw that as an
opportunity for a growth oh it's
wonderful I I still insist you know I
know I'm repeating myself but uh but but
it is not necessarily from academics and
from professional scientists that the
developments come from I mean didn't
didn't the guys who developed Koda
Chrome wen't they musicians you know um
so uh it's it's really uh I expect um
the Innovations to come from the outside
as much as from the inside of the
so-called scientific establishment
absolutely and that's going to happen
with an amateur uh who is paying real
close
attention
okay well Mark I want to thank you for
taking this time to uh talk it's been a
great interview I'm sure people
appreciate you taking the time as well
toh come on and talk about holography
there's not too many outlets out there
you know where someone can uh you know
come on and uh Listen to Somebody talk
about something that they enjoy so thank
you very much oh it's been my pleasure
and if I grab uh one of the pictures of
your Holograms would it be okay to put
it on holog sure people steal stuff
said yeah I know all right well Mark
thank you very much send I'll send you
an email when the show's getting ready
to go up
okay